Puerto Rican Oral History Project records 1976.001
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Negron, Sophie, 1974 August 27; 1976.001.046
  In this interview, Sophie Negrón talks about living conditions, ethnic composition, and shop owners of the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood. She briefly narrates what life was like during the Great Depression and mentions several political figures and community leader such as Sister Carmelita, Carlos Tapia, and Gilberto Concepción de Gracia. Although she was not directly involved in any political organizations, Negrón describes how she was kept up to date regarding the current political climate and social struggles through her visitors and the radio. Negrón reflects on how the Puerto Rican community and their recreational activities have changed and concludes that Puerto Rican values and culture are being left behind by younger generations. Interview in English and Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Negron, Sophie, 1891-; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Cultural assimilation |z United States; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York Region |x Religion; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs |y 20th century
- Oliveras, Edna Rosado, 1975 January 19; 1976.001.047
  Edna Rosado Oliveras was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1934. She lived in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn for eight years and then moved to the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood. At the time of the 1975 interview, Oliveras was forty years old and a housewife. She worked as an assistant teacher with the Department of Education and as a Sunday school teacher. She was an active member of the Seneca Club, the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA), and the First Spanish Presbyterian Church in Brooklyn. Edna Rosado Oliveras died in Brooklyn in April, 1984.
  In this interview, Edna Rosado Oliveras discusses living conditions in the Williamsburg and Brooklyn Heights neighborhoods of Brooklyn, as well the changes that occurred once the Puerto Rican population in said neighborhoods increased. Oliveras talks about the charitable activities of the civic, religious, and political organizations to which she belongs. She also mentions notable members of these organizations and their efforts to enhance the quality of life for Puerto Ricans in New York. Oliveras discusses the need for immigrants to overcome language barriers and learn the language of the country in which they currently live in while also retaining their cultural identity. The flaws embedded in public assistance programs such as Welfare are reflected upon as well. Interview in Spanish and English conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Oliveras, Edna Rosado, 1934-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Public welfare |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women |x Political activity |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Cultural assimilation |z United States; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Young Men's Christian associations |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Padilla de Armas, Encarnacion, 1974 October 21; 1976.001.048
  Encarnación Padilla de Armas came to Brooklyn in 1926, at age sixteen. Her residency there was sporadic since then. She traveled extensively through all of the Spanish-speaking countries of the world. Padilla de Armas obtained a bachelor’s degree and an honorary doctorate from Fordham University. She worked for sixteen years with the Liberal Party. In 1974, she had organized a community group of elderly, urban Puerto Ricans, was retired and a widow. Padilla de Armas died in 1992.
  In the interview, Encarnación Padilla de Armas begins by describing her involvement with the Puerto Rican community in Brooklyn in the 1920s. She reminisces about her first years in America as a teenager, and then continues with a description of her involvement with certain organizations and civic leaders, as well as her personal interest in Puerto Rican citizens in need. She closes by evaluating and forecasting both political and social matters concerning the Puerto Rican community of Brooklyn in the 1970s. Interview conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Denis, Antonia; Padilla de Armas, Encarnacion, 1910-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Rican women |x Political activity |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Cultural assimilation |z United States; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Intellectual life; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico; Red Hook (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Perez, Nick, 1974 November 5; 1976.001.049
  Nick Perez arrived in New York City in 1930 at the age of twenty-five. He came to reside in Brooklyn circa 1934 and remained until at least 1974. With little formal education, Perez worked mostly in service industry workplaces like restaurants. However, he enrolled in several training programs and qualified as an auto mechanic. Perez was retired and living alone in 1974. He died in Miami, Florida in 1997.
  In the interview, Nick Perez gives a chronological account of his workplaces and work experience; beginning with his first job in the States at the Hotel New Yorker in Manhattan to his last job as an auto mechanic instructor at Mobilization for Youth, an anti-poverty program. He discusses job hunting experiences, his divorce and immediate family, and his visits to Puerto Rico. Interview conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Perez, Nick, 1905-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Puerto Ricans |x Cultural assimilation |z United States; Puerto Ricans |x Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Work environment |z New York (State) |z New York
- Plasencia, Gonzalo, 1974 November 4; 1976.001.050
  Born in Puerto Rico, 1909, Gonzalo Plasencia arrived in Brooklyn in 1929 and, after a brief stay with an aunt in Upper Manhattan, he became a longtime resident. As a man of letters - in addition to sports - he had been active in the Puerto Rican community for decades. Plasencia was responsible for establishing a Puerto Rican baseball league in Brooklyn. A former employee of the Sweets Company of America's Tootsie Roll factory in Manhattan, Plasencia was semi-retired and working as a columnist for the Sunset News in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Sunset Park at the time of the interview in 1974.
  In the interview, Gonzalo Plasencia offers information on the employment problems faced by Puerto Ricans, as well as the historic problems between the Puerto Rican community and the New York police. He also discusses the origin and formation of the Puerto Rican Pioneers Parade, as well as the advocacy group United Puerto Rican Organization of Sunset Park (UPROSE). In addition, there is mention of several well-known Puerto Rican individuals, such as Carlos Tapia, Antonia Denis and Ramon González. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Denis, Antonia; New York (N.Y.). Police Department.; Pioneers Day Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.).; Plasencia, Gonzalo, 1909-; Tapia, Carlos; Tootsie Roll Industries.; United Puerto Rican Organization of Sunset Park.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State); Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration; Work environment |z United States
- Pratts, Francisco, 1974 October 14; 1976.001.051
  In 1921, at about age twenty, Francisco Pratts arrived in New York City and moved to Brooklyn shortly thereafter and remained a resident well into the 1980s. A merchant marine and dockworker on Brooklyn's ports and a veteran of World War II, Pratts was a cook before he retired in the early 1970s. Married with four grown children at the time of this 1974 interview, he hoped he and his wife could return to Puerto Rico in retirement. Francisco Pratts died in Brooklyn in 1987.
  In the interview, Francisco Pratts gives his account of the social and economic challenges of Puerto Ricans new to Brooklyn during the 1920s and 1930s. He speaks with some severe language and bias about the conflicts and confrontations of Puerto Ricans and Italians. Pratts also reflects on political dealings that affected the community and individuals such as Carlos Tapia, James Kelly, and others who were active in establishing political clubs. Interview conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Kelly, James; Pratts, Francisco, 1902-; Tapia, Carlos; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Discrimination in employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Docks |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Waterfronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z United States
- Ramos, Juan, 1973 August 25; 1976.001.052
  Juan Ramos was born in Puerto Rico in 1908 and raised in Bayamon and San Juan. He arrived in New York in 1926, living in Upper Manhattan until 1945 - at which point he moved to the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn. He was trained as a baker in Puerto Rico and had labored in New York City as a factory worker. At the time of the interview in 1973, Ramos was living in Williamsburg with his wife and youngest son and working in a hospital as a nurse's aide. He was the father of five children.
  In the interview, Juan Ramos briefly discusses his childhood in Puerto Rico and 1926 arrival in New York. He recounts his experience as a Puerto Rican in the United States during the Great Depression, offering a vivid description of economic conditions between 1928 and 1932. He recalls the ethnic friction that arose between Puerto Ricans, Jews, and Italians during the 1930s and 1940s. Ramos gives detailed information about Puerto Ricans in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn after 1945. Ramos also compares the small and tightknit New York City Puerto Rican community of the 1920s, 1930s, and 1940s with subsequent generations. Interview in Spanish conducted by Mayda Cortiella.
  Ramos, Juan, 1908-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.)
- Rivera, Cecilio, 1974 June 20; 1976.001.053
  Cecilio Rivera was born in Puerto Rico in 1903. He arrived in Brooklyn in 1929 and resided in the Williamsburg neighborhood up until 1949 - at which time he and his family moved to Brentwood, New York. As a retired businessman, Rivera had first worked in numerous grocery stores before eventually purchasing his own bodega. The personal connections he made while working in local shops and delivering groceries throughout Brooklyn served him well, as he went on to found and/or participate in several civic and social organizations revolving around the Puerto Rican community. These include the Baldorioty Democratic Club, the Puerto Rican Civic Association, the Puerto Rican Merchants Association - in which Rivera served as the first president - and the Pan American Civic Association, which he founded after relocating to Eastern Long Island.
  In the first of two interviews, Cecilio Rivera offers personal details and touches on his experience as a small business owner and activist in Brooklyn's Puerto Rican community. Rivera discusses in brief, the formation, function, and participation within political clubs and organizations. In addition, he speaks on Carlos Tapia, the general job prospects of the Puerto Rican community, and Puerto Rican identity in America. Rivera closes with some reflection on his own business opportunities, his insight into his brief time at Pfizer, and leaving Brooklyn for New York suburbia. Interview conducted by Monte Rivera.
  Pfizer Inc.; Rivera, Cecilio, 1903-; Tapia, Carlos; Bodegas |z New York (State) |z New York; Brentwood (N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |x Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Rivera, Cecilio, 1974 November 2; 1976.001.054
  In the second of two interviews, Cecilio Rivera offers a personal chronology - and critique - as a result of his experience as a small business owner, activist, and benefactor of Brooklyn's Puerto Rican community. He gives a number of specific events with corresponding dates related to various clubs and organizations he was associated with, such as the Baldorioty Democratic Club, the Puerto Rican Civic Association, and the Puerto Rican Merchants Association - in which he served as the first president. Rivera discusses in detail the formation, function, and organization of these groups. In addition there is biographical data on Carlos Tapia, Louis Weber, and Pedro Tejada, as well as other figures involved with the Puerto Rican community. Never properly introduced, Rivera's wife, Jean Carrero, interjects often in the background and occasionally in the foreground. Interview in Spanish and English conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Baldorioty Democratic Club.; Pan American Civic Association.; Puerto Rican Civic Association.; Puerto Rican Merchants Association.; Rivera, Cecilio, 1903-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Long Island (N.Y.); Markets |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Politics and government |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Puerto Rico; Suffolk County (N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Rodriguez, Juana Weber, 1974 October 25; 1976.001.055
  Juana Weber Rodríguez was born in Puerto Rico in 1897. She landed in Brooklyn with her daughter on May 30, 1926, after her husband had arrived in March of the same year. Along with her family, Rodríguez resided in the Red Hook and Carroll Gardens neighborhoods of Brooklyn. Her husband labored as a factory worker, an employee of the Betances Democratic Club (founded by Rodríguez's brother Louis Felipe Weber), and as a merchant marine, while Rodríguez worked as a housewife and mother. At the time of the interview in 1974, she had been living in the Howard Beach neighborhood of Queens for approximately two years.
  In the interview, Juana Weber Rodríguez recalls Brooklyn's relatively small and tight-knit Puerto Rican community of the 1920s and 1930s. She recounts the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Red Hook, Carroll Gardens and Columbia Height's waterfront with special attention paid to the early beginnings of Puerto Rican (and Hispanic) businesses and political clubs, as well as ethnic diversity. Rodríguez also discusses discrimination, as well as attempts by her brother Louis Felipe Weber and other community leaders to aid, advocate for, and encourage political participation within the Puerto Rican community. There is also a brief discussion of Spanish-language newspapers, as well as a comparison between Puerto Ricans during the interwar period and the 1970s. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.
  Betances Club.; Democratic Party (New York, N.Y.).; Rodriguez, Juana Weber, 1897-; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Civic leaders |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Columbia Heights (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Red Hook (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Rodriguez, Maria, 1974 November 15; 1976.001.056
  María Rodríguez was born in Juana Díaz, Puerto Rico in 1911. She arrived in Brooklyn in 1945 and has lived there since her arrival. The daughter of farmers from the Puerto Rican countryside, she had limited educational opportunities and trained as a sewing machine operator. Rodríguez followed in the footsteps of an older sister and cousin by coming to New York, a move she says was made for the adventure rather than economic reasons. After first residing in the Bronx, she moved to Fulton Street in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. At the time of the interview in 1974 she resided in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn with her husband Pedro Rodríguez.
  In the interview, María Rodríguez relates information about Brooklyn factories during the growth of labor unions in the 1940s, including the treatment of workers - elaborating specifically on the conditions for Puerto Ricans - and the attitude of Puerto Ricans in the factory toward organized labor. As a civic-minded individual, Rodríguez offers insight into the everyday experiences of Puerto Ricans, including housing conditions and their relations with other ethnic groups. She looks back on various social clubs, including organizers of El Desfile Puertorriqueño (The Puerto Rican Parade), of which Rodríguez is a founding member. She talks extensively about unity and social progress in New York's Puerto Rican community. Rodríguez's husband Pedro was also interviewed in the couple's home on the same day. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Rodriguez, Maria, 1911-; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State); Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Political clubs |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Rodriguez, Pedro, 1974 November 15; 1976.001.057
  Pedro M. Rodríguez arrived in Brooklyn in April, 1945 and has resided here since his arrival. Born the son of farmers in Ponce, Puerto Rico, he was a carpenter by trade with a limited formal education who worked in Brooklyn's factories for most of his life. In his new, adopted homeland, Rodríguez was decidedly civic-minded and often engaged in community affairs. He served as vice president of La Confederacion General Puertorriqueña, a Brooklyn-based Puerto Rican advocacy group. At the time of the interview in 1974 he resided in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn with his wife Maria Rodríguez.
  In the interview, Pedro M. Rodríguez recalls his first impressions of New York upon his arrival at Pennsylvania Station in 1945, his first home in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Clinton Hill, and his first job in a factory in the Bronx. He reveals the Puerto Rican search for a unified identity and its role in initiating organizations - groups which, in his view, would help meet the needs of New York's Puerto Rican community. He specifically describes the origin and functions of La Confederacion General Puertorriqueña, as well as a recounting of discrimination directed toward Puerto Ricans in Brooklyn. Rodríguez's wife, Maria, was also interviewed in the couple's home on the same day. Interview in Spanish conducted by Jaime Barreto.
  Rodriguez, Pedro, 1912-; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Factories |z New York (State); Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |x Employment |z New York (State) |z New York; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Economic conditions; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Ethnic identity; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century; Puerto Rico; Race discrimination |z New York (State) |z New York; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); United States |x Emigration and immigration
- Rodriguez, Ramon, 1974 October 29; 1976.001.058
  Ramón Rodríguez was born in Puerto Rico in 1901. He arrived in Brooklyn in 1927, working at Acme Backing Corporation, a rubber cement factory, for twenty-three years. Rodríguez lived in various locations in the neighborhood of Downtown Brooklyn, moving to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1946. Despite being a factory worker with little formal education, he remained active in his community, becoming acquainted with many of its leading figures.
  In the interview, Ramón Rodríguez recounts the first generation of Puerto Rican grocery stores in Brooklyn during the late 1920s and 1930s. He specifies such stores by name. In addition, Rodríguez relates information on living conditions in the 1930s, as well as what he describes as the poor relationship between the police and Brooklyn's Puerto Rican community. There is also a detailed account of renowned local figures such as Sister Carmelita, Jesus Colón, Louis Weber, and Carlos Tapia. Interview in Spanish conducted by John D. Vazquez.